Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ansgarzerfass (LinkedIn) www.zerfass.de (Personal) www.communicationmanagement.de (Company)

Top Skills

Qualitative Research
Corporate Communications
Strategic Communication

Languages

English (Full Professional)
German (Native or Bilingual)

Honors-Awards

Pathfinder Award

Distinguished Scholar in Public Relations

Jackson Jackson & Wagner Award

PR Head of the Year 2005 in Germany (PR-Kopf des Jahres)

PR Report Award 2010 "Innovative PR Strategy" for a student marketing campaign (Leipzig University)

Prof. Dr. Ansgar Zerfass

Professor and Chair of Strategic Communication at Leipzig University & Professor of Communication and Leadership at BI Norwegian Business School, Oslo

Greater Leipzig Area

Summary

Dr. Ansgar Zerfass is Professor and Chair of Strategic
Communication at the Institute of Communication and Media
Studies at Leipzig University, Germany. He is also Professor of
Communication and Leadership at BI Norwegian Business School,
Oslo, as well as editor of the "International Journal of Strategic
Communication", USA, and Plank Scholar at The Plank Center for
Leadership and Communication at the University of Alabama, USA.
He serves as board member and PR Division chair 2021-2023 for
the International Communication Association (ICA), Washington,
D.C.

So far, he has published 38 books and 400 journal articles, book chapters and study reports in multiple languages in the areas of Corporate Communications, Measurement and Evaluation, Digital Communication and International / Comparative Communication. In June 2020, Google Scholar listed Dr. Zerfass as the most cited researcher in strategic communication, corporate communication and communication management worldwide and among the TOP-3 scholars globally in public relations.

Dr. Zerfass leads the largest study series on strategic communication worldwide, the European Communication Monitor that covers over 80 countries with its affiliates, the Asia-Pacific, Latin American and North American Communication Monitor. He has also initiated the Academic Society of Corporate Management & Leadership, a network of chief communication officers from almost 40 blue-chip companies and leading universities in the field.

Experience

Leipzig University 15 years 10 months

Professor and Chair of Strategic Communication October 2014 - Present (7 years 7 months)

Page 1 of 4

Leipzig, Sachsen, Deutschland

Full professor and chair at the Institute of Communication and Media Studies. Head of the master program Communication Management, the #1 ranked graduate program in the field of public relations and strategic communication in the German speaking countries since 2007. Developing international collaborations and projects; mentoring next-generation researchers and students (24 awards for master and PhD students for the best theses in the field nationally or internationally so far).

Professor of Communication Management July 2006 - September 2014 (8 years 3 months)

Full professor at the Institute of Communication and Media Studies; researching and teaching in various study programs. Services as Head of the Institute and Vice Dean of the Faculty.

BI Norwegian Business School Professor of Communication and Leadership January 2013 - Present (9 years 4 months)

Adjunct professor in the Department of Communication and Culture at one of the leading business schools in the Nordics.

International Journal of Strategic Communication (Routledge Publishers)

Editor

January 2009 - Present (13 years 4 months)

Heading the editorial team of a renowned academic journal (together with Prof. Derina Holtzhausen, PhD., now with Prof. Kelly Werder, PhD) and an edictal team of professors from more than 20 country around the world. Responsible for profiling the journal and rising its impact (now #2 communications journal in the field of communication management, PR, strategic communication).

EUPRERA European Public Relations Education and Research Association

President

January 2014 - December 2015 (2 years)

Heading the European association of public relations and communication management researchers with approx. 500 members from more than 40 countries. Voluntary work.

MFG Medien- und Filmgesellschaft Baden-Württemberg mbH

9 years 8 months

Member of the Executive Board January 2001 - June 2006 (5 years 6 months)

Stuttgart, Baden-Württemberg, Germany

Responsibility for several units (communications, training and events, research and knowledge transfer) and overall management responsibilities. Developing new projects and acquiring funding from private and public sources, e.g. the European Union. Representing the company and the state of Baden-Württemberg in various national and international settings.

Head of communication and digital media November 1996 - December 2000 (4 years 2 months) Stuttgart, Baden-Württemberg, Germany

Building up the communications team at the state's competence center for innovation and media. Planning and executing major projects for the government of Baden-Württemberg, e.g. project management for the first online portal baden-wuerttemberg.de, heading the content team, organizing national events and trade fairs, and projects representing the regional media industry at international trade fairs in the United States and across Europe.

University of Erlangen-Nuremberg Research Associate / Assistant Professor December 1990 - October 1996 (5 years 11 months) Nuremberg, Bavaria, Germany

Research assistant at the Chair of Business Administration and Strategic Management (Prof. Dr. Dr. h. c. mult. Horst Steinmann). Establishing the research field "Corporate communication". Teaching and research in the field "Business and society / Business ethics".

Institute für Informatik / Schmitt Computersysteme Information Technology Consultant and Trainer October 1986 - December 1989 (3 years 3 months) Nuremberg, Bavaria, Germany

Working as a sales consultant and further education trainer in information systems for two companies - part-time (50%) and full-time (100%) jobs during studies.

Education

University of Erlangen-Nuremberg

Dr. habil. (Habilitation = second Ph.D.), Communication Science · (December 2005)

University of Erlangen-Nuremberg

Dr. rer. pol. (Ph.D. in Business Administration), Strategic Management · (November 1995)

University of Erlangen-Nuremberg

Dipl.-Kfm. (Univ.), Business Administration and Management, General · (November 1990)

Platen-Gymnasium Ansbach

Abitur (German equivalent to secondary school) · (June 1984)